Guide to the Steve Bristow Papers M1887
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Steve Bristow papers
1969-1996
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Bristow, Steve, 1950-2015
M1887
12.25 Linear Feet (23 boxes)
Access to Collection
The materials are open for research use. Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Acquisition Information
This collection given by Steve Bristow to Stanford University, Special Collections in April, 2012.
Biographical / Historical
Steve Bristow (1950-2015) was a video game pioneer known especially for his work on arcade games at Atari. Bristow was born in California and lived there his entire life. In 1971, while studying at University of California-Berkeley and interning at Ampex under the supervision of Nolan Bushnell and Ted Dabney, Bristow worked on circuitry for Computer Space, the first commercially sold coin-operated video game. After Ampex decided not to pursue the video game market, Bushnell left for Nutting Associates, and Bristow followed in March 1972, creating a two-person version of Computer Space with his wife, among other games. Around this time the Bristows also maintained and collected money from arcade machines in Berkeley as a sideline.
After graduation, Barstow went straight to Bushnell’s new company, known as Atari. As head of Coin Engineering he helped develop multi-user versions of Pong, Indy 800 (one of the first arcade racing games), as well as the company-saving Tank and Breakout. Among his various roles, he was involved with the Electronic Board Game Division and was Plant Manager of Pinball Production. Bristow was more or less in charge of Atari's arcade division until 1979 when he transitioned to the Consumer and Computer Group, where he helped put Atari’s home computer line into production. Not long after a management decision to bring out a successor to the 2600 rather than license Nintendo’s new game system, Bristow left Atari and worked as an electrical engineer. He passed away in February 2015 at the age of 65.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of business papers such as reports, legal & patent documents, and sales & trade show material; notebooks; service manuals & user guides; schematics; advertisements;, articles and photographs. Most of the papers concern Bristow's career at Atari.
Video games.; Coin-operated machines; Video game design; Video arcades; Bristow, Steve, 1950-2015; Atari, Inc.
- Series 1: Personal Papers
  - University of California College of Engineering Papers: 1970, 1 of 2. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - University of California College of Engineering Papers: 1970, 2 of 2. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Engineering School Personal Papers: ca. 1971-1972. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence and Papers, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Personal Planner, 1981. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Engineering Notebook, March 1981. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Engineering Notebook, May 1981. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Engineering Notebook, July 1981. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Engineering Notebook, October 1981. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Engineering Notebook, February 1982. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Engineering Notebook, April 1982. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Engineering Notebook, October 1982. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Engineering Notebook, December 1982. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Engineering Notebook, ca. 1983. (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Series 2: Legal Documents, Patents, and Lawsuits
  - Atari, Inc. vs. Mar-Quin Company, ca. 1975. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Papers shown to Magnavox, ca. 1972-1976. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Alpex Computer vs. Nintendo, ca. 1976. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous Patents and Notes: n.d., 1 of 3. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous Patents and Notes: n.d., 2 of 3. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous Patents and Notes: n.d., 3 of 3. (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Series 3: Manuals and Schematics
  - CAL 6400 Fortran Guide: Users Manual: 1969, 1 of 2. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - CAL 6400 Fortran Guide: Users Manual: 1969, 2 of 2. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Pin Pong Operation and Maintenance Manual, 1974. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Trak 10 Operation and Maintenance Manual, 1974. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Qwak Service Information and Schematics, 1974. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Tank Operation and Service Manuals, 1975-1978. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Indy 800 Service Information, ca. 1975. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Super Bug and Drag Racer schematics, ca. 1976. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Color Monitor Troubleshooting Manuals, 1976. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Television Interface Adaptor 1A Manual, ca. 1976. (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Kiosk Operation and Maintenance Supplement, 1976. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Night Driver Operation and Service Manual, 1976. (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Breakout Operation and Service Manual, 1976. (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - LeMans Operation and Service Manual, 1976. (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Super Bug and Drag Racer Schematics, ca. 1976. (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Williams Parts Catalogs, ca. 1977-1978. (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Signetics PVI Manual, 1977. (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Airborne Avenger Operator Information, 1977. (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Drag Race Operation and Service Manual, 1977. (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Triple Hunt Operation and Service Manual, 1977. (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Symphomatic Technical Brochures, 1977. (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - F-1 Operation Manual and Parts Catalog, 1977. (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Sprint 8 Operation and Service Manual, 1977. (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Canyon Bomber Operation and Service Manual, 1977. (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Atari Poolshark Parts Catalog, 1977. (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - The Atarians Operation and Service Manual, 1977. (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Super Bug Operation and Service Manual, 1977. (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Two-Game Module Operation, Maintenance, and Service Manual, 1978. (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Fire Truck Operation and Service Manuals, 1978. (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Atari Pinball Games Illustrated Parts Catalog, 1978. (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Superman Pinball Operation and Service Manuals, 1978. (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Computer Space Service Manual, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 31a)
  - Pinball Troubleshooting Guide, 1978. (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Cyan Engineering Papers, 1978. (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - D. Gottlieb & Co. Parts Catalogs, 1978-1987. (Box 7, Folder 34)
  - Interactive Terminals/Viewdata Papers, 1979-1980. (Box 7, Folder 35)
  - Teletext Papers, 1979-1981. (Box 7, Folder 36)
  - Atari Basketball Operation and Service Manual, 1979. (Box 7, Folder 37)
  - Visicalc: Operations Manual, 1979. (Box 7, Folder 39)
  - Hercules Parts Catalog and Service Manuals, 1979. (Box 7, Folder 40)
  - Subs Operation and Service Manual, 1979. (Box 8, Folder 41)
  - Assembler Manual, 1979. (Box 8, Folder 42)
  - 4-Player Football Operation and Service Manual, 1979. (Box 8, Folder 43)
  - Bally Pinball 1979-1 Parts Catalog, 1979. (Box 8, Folder 44)
  - Lunar Lander Operation and Service Manual, 1979. (Box 8, Folder 45)
  - Atari 400/800 DOS II Reference Manuals, 1980-1981. (Box 8, Folder 46)
  - Battle Zone Operation and Service Manuals, 1980. (Box 8, Folder 47)
  - Monte Carlo Operation and Service Manual, 1980. (Box 8, Folder 48)
  - Atari Telelink Manual, 1980. (Box 8, Folder 49)
  - Atari 850 Operator's Manual and Notes, ca. 1980. (Box 8, Folder 50)
  - Atari 825 Printer Operator's Manual, 1980. (Box 9, Folder 51)
  - Atari Basic Manual, 1980. (Box 9, Folder 52)
  - Atari 400/800 Statistics I Manual, 1980. (Box 9, Folder 53)
  - Missile Command Operation and Service Manual, 1980. (Box 9, Folder 54)
  - Atari 810 Disk Peripheral Description, 1980. (Box 9, Folder 55)
  - Asteroids Operation and Service Manuals, 1980. (Box 9, Folder 56)
  - Atari: The Book, Guide to Operation and Service, 1980. (Box 9, Folder 57)
  - Pre-1980 Audio Detailsm, ca. 1980. (Box 9, Folder 58)
  - Atari 1050 Manuals, 1981-1983. (Box 9, Folder 59)
  - Robotics Age Magazine, 1981. (Box 9, Folder 60)
  - Atari 810 Manuals, 1981. (Box 9, Folder 61)
  - Firefox Operators Manuals, 1983. (Box 9, Folder 62)
  - Xevious Schematic Package, 1983. (Box 9, Folder 63)
  - Atari 1030 Modem Owner's Guide, 1983. (Box 9, Folder 64)
  - Amiga ROM Kernel Manual, 1985. (Box 10, Folder 65)
  - Nintendo Circuit Diagrams and Schematics (Binder 5 of 5), ca. 1986. (Box 10, Folder 66)
  - Nintendo Circuit Diagrams and Schematics (Binder 5 of 5), ca. 1986. (Box 10, Folder 67)
  - Nintendo Circuit Diagrams and Schematics (Binder 5 of 5), ca. 1986. (Box 10, Folder 68)
  - F-14 Tomcat Instruction Manual, 1987. (Box 10, Folder 69)
  - Commodore A500 User's Manual, ca. 1987. (Box 10, Folder 70)
  - Big Mouth Operator's Manual & Schematics, ca. 1988. (Box 11, Folders 71)
  - Commodore Amiga Enhancer Software Manual, 1989. (Box 11, Folders 72)
  - Elvira Pinball Operation and Service Manual, 1989. (Box 11, Folders 73)
  - Motion Board Bi-Plane Schematics, ca. 1989. (Box 11, Folders 74)
  - Slap Shot Hockey Preliminary Manual, 1989. (Box 11, Folders 75)
  - Burle Service Manual TC7000 Series, 1989. (Box 11, Folders 76)
  - Bally Pool Sharks Operations Manual, 1990. (Box 11, Folders 77)
  - Whirlwind Operations Manual, 1990. (Box 11, Folders 78)
  - Data East Installation and Service Manuals, 1990-1991. (Box 11, Folders 79)
  - Wacky Gator Installation and Service Manuals, 1990-1992. (Box 11, Folders 80)
  - Steel Gunner Operation Manual, 1990. (Box 11, Folders 81)
  - Captain America and the Avengers Manuals, 1991. (Box 11, Folder 82)
  - Cosmo Gang Preliminary Manual, 1991. (Box 12, Folder 83)
  - Jaguar Development System: 1994, 1 of 2. (Box 12, Folder 84)
  - Jaguar Development System: 1994, 2 of 2. (Box 12, Folder 85)
  - Atari 800/810 DOS Manual Draft, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 86)
  - Taito Parts Catalog, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 87)
  - Dark Seal II: Wizard Fire Instructions (in Japanese), n.d. (Box 12, Folder 88)
  - Atari ProBall Instruction Manual, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 89)
  - Wurlitzer Phonograph Service Manual, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 90)
  - Middle Earth Operation and Service Manual, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 91)
  - Payphone Network Manager Software Manual, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 92)
  - Tec Videoelectronics Service Manual, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 93)
  - Unidentified Schematic, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 94)
  - Flyball Schematics, 1976. (Flat-box 22, Folder 1)
  - Kee Games Schematic, 1974. (Flat-box 22, Folder 2)
  - Car Board schematics, 1975. (Flat-box 22, Folder 3)
  - Digital Panel Drive Pinball, 1976. (Flat-box 22, Folder 4)
  - Unidentified schematic, n.d. (Flat-box 22, Folder 5)
  - Power Supply Board schematic, 1976. (Flat-box 22, Folder 6)
  - Unidentified schematics, 1976. (Flat-box 22, Folder 8)
  - Frenzy schematics, 1975. (Flat-box 22, Folder 9)
  - Cops & Robbers schematics, 1976. (Flat-box 22, Folder 10)
  - Unidentified schematic, n.d. (Flat-box 22, Folder 11)
  - Atari Poster, n.d. (Flat-box 22, Folder 12)
  - Two Game Module Operation, Maintenance, and Service Manual, 1978. (Box 23, Folder 95)
  - Indy 800 Service Information, ca. 1975. (Box 23, Folder 96)
- Series 4: Business Papers and Trade Show Reports
  - Trade Show Photographs, 1974-1984. (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Atari Drafting Standards Manual, ca. 1975-1977. (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Atari Internal Company Papers, ca. 1976-1986. (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - IAAPA and MOA Reports: 1976, 1 of 2. (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - IAAPA and MOA Reports: 1976, 2 of 2. (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - MOA Show Reports, 1977-1978. (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Atari Research on Motorala, ca. 1977-1981. (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Home Computer Show Chicago, 1977. (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Atari Video Display Research, 1978-1981. (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Atari: Dealer Merchandising Plans, ca. 1980-1981. (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Atari Almanac, ca. 1980. (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Memos and Notes regarding Home Computing Technology, 1980-1994. (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Atari Reference Manuals and News Releases, ca. 1980. (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - IAAPA Show Report, 1980. (Box 14, Folder 14)
  - Toy Show Report, 1980. (Box 14, Folder 15)
  - Atari FAQ and How-to Papers, 1981-1986. (Box 14, Folder 16)
  - WEA Germany Report, 1981. (Box 14, Folder 17)
  - AMOA Report, 1981. (Box 14, Folder 18)
  - Atari Almanac, 1981. (Box 14, Folder 19)
  - Atari Commercial Storyboards, 1981. (Box 14, Folder 20)
  - Vidcom Show Report, 1982. (Box 14, Folder 21)
  - JAA Coin-Op Show Report: 1981, 1 of 2. (Box 15, Folder 22)
  - JAA Coin-Op Show Report: 1981, 2 of 2. (Box 15, Folder 23)
  - CES Report: June 1982, 1 of 3. (Box 15, Folder 24)
  - CES Report: June 1982, 2 of 3. (Box 15, Folder 25)
  - CES Report: June 1982, 3 of 3. (Box 15, Folder 26)
  - Atari Coin-op Press Clippings, 1982. (Box 16, Folder 27)
  - Atari Research Report, ca. 1982. (Box 16, Folder 28)
  - Wescon Show Report, 1982. (Box 16, Folder 29)
  - MOA Show Report, 1982. (Box 16, Folder 30)
  - Comdex Show Report, 1982. (Box 16, Folder 31)
  - Far East Electronics Show Report, 1982. (Box 16, Folder 32)
  - Japan Telecommunications Show Report, 1982. (Box 16, Folder 33)
  - Toy Show Report, 1982. (Box 16, Folder 34)
  - Paris Electronics Show, 1982. (Box 17, Folder 35)
  - Atari Executive Directory, 1983. (Box 17, Folder 36)
  - AMOA Report, 1983. (Box 17, Folder 37)
  - CES Report, 1983. (Box 17, Folder 38)
  - CES Las Vegas, 1983. (Box 17, Folder 39)
  - Chicago CES Show: 1984, 1 of 2. (Box 17, Folder 40)
  - Chicago CES Show: 1984, 2 of 2. (Box 17, Folder 41)
  - Chicago CES Report, 1985. (Box 18, Folder 42)
  - Atari Alumni Directory, 1992. (Box 18, Folder 43)
  - Atari Inter-Company Telephone Directory, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 44)
  - Atari: Misc. Reference Guides and Articles. (Box 18, Folder 45)
  - Photo album of various trade shows and events, 1974-1979. (Flat-box 21, Folder 1)
- Series 5: Magazines, advertisements, articles
  - Atari Ads, Promotional Materials, and Catalogs, ca. 1976-1988. (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - "TV Games - Just the Beginning" session papers, 1977. (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Notes and Documents regarding "Chapter 7: Displays", 1981. (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Video Games Magazine, 1982. (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Atari Connection Magazine, 1983. (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Alpha Omega Amusements, 1986-1987. (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Tiger Electronics Learning Ads, 1989. (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Nintendo Playchoice 10 Papers, 1989. (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Data East Coin-Op Catalogs, 1991. (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - Sharp Imager Electronics Inc. Papers, 1991. (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - Astro Game Products, 1992-1996. (Box 18, Folder 11)
  - Itek Defense Electronics Wallchart, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - Alter Enterprises Article, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous Advertisements, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 14)
- Series 6: Hardware and Software
  - Atari: 5 1/4'' inch Floppy Discs. (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Atari 850 Console, n.d. (Box 20, Folder 2)